嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么今天我们会讲OpenGL中的顶点数组
so today we're gonna be talking all about vertex arrays in OpenGL of course
到目前为止, 我们已经讨论了什么是顶点缓冲区
so, so far we've been talking about what a vertex buffer is
什么是索引缓冲区或元素缓冲区
what a index buffer is or an element buffer
我们讲过着色器
we've talked about shaders
我们讲了很多OpenGL的基本概念甚至一般的图形编程
we've talked about a lot of kind of basic concepts of OpenGL and even graphics programming in general
但OpenGL实际上有一个顶点数组
but OpenGL actually has something called a vertex array
乍一看
and at first glance
你可能会说, 顶点数组, 顶点缓冲区
you might be like well vertex array vertex buffer
它们之间的区别是什么
what is the difference
它们听起来非常相似, 确实如此
they sound extremely similar, and they are
而更疯狂的是
and to make it even even crazier
所以那个确实意味着这不是特别疯狂
so does that mean this isn't particularly crazy
但更疯狂的是
but to make it even crazier
这并不是DirectX等其他渲染接口中真正存在的东西
this isn't really something that exists in other rendering apis like DirectX
顶点数组是OpenGL的一个特殊之处
vertex arrays are a bit of an OpenGL special
或者如果你喜欢的话, 也可以说是一个OpenGL原始接口
or an OpenGL original if you like
它们基本上是一种通过一种特定的规范绑定顶点缓冲区的方式
and what they basically are are a way to bind buffers vertex buffers with a certain kind of specification
用于那个实际顶点缓冲区的布局
for the layout of that actual vertex buffer
那么让我们来看看
so let's take a look at
我的意思是快速地看一些代码
what I mean by that by just looking at some code real quick
那么在我们的应用中, 我们在这里创建了这个buffer
so in our application, we have this buffer that we're creating over here
确切地说, 这是个数组buffer
specifically there's array buffer
包含了我们所有的顶点数据
which contains all of our vertex data
并且实际上, 你们可能已经从之前的视频中注意到了
and actually you may have noticed from previous episodes
我在这里写了6作为一个size
that I have six written here as a size
如果我们有6个顶点, 但显然我们只有4个
so as if we have six vertices, clearly we have four
根据这个, 这是个漏洞
according to this, that's a bug
我们把这个设为4来修复那个
let's fix that by setting this to four
但这个顶点缓冲区只包含了这些顶点位置
but this vertex buffer contains these vertex positions
这些顶点, 这个顶点的所有数据
these vertex, all of this vertex data
在这个例子中就是四个顶点的顶点位置
which in this case is just vertex positions for four vertices
然后, 在我们创建了缓冲区之后, 也做了绑定
and then, after we've created the buffer, and we've bound
我们已经设置了数据和所有这些
and we've set the data and all of that
and then, after we've created the buffer, and we've bound
我们已经设置了数据和所有这些
and we've set the data and all of that
我们实际上启用了顶点属性, 然后在这里指定实际数据的布局
we actually enable the vertex attribute, and then specify the layout of this actual data here
通过说基本上每个顶点, 每个顶点是两个浮点数
by saying that basically every vertex, each vertex is two floats
然后那个就是stride, 这个顶点到下个顶点的间隔, 对吧
and then that's the stride, kind of vertex to vertex, right
我们还指定了这个属性的偏移量等等
and we also specify like the offset of this attribute and all of that
所以我们基本上只是指定这个实际顶点缓冲区的布局
so we basically just specify the layout of this actual vertex buffer
现在, 一个顶点数组对象实际上允许我们做的
now, what a vertex array object actually lets us do
就是绑定我们指定的顶点规范
is kind of bind that vertex specification that we specify
通过使用这个vertexAttribPointer
by using this vertex vertexAttribPointer
到实际缓冲区, 到实际顶点缓冲区或一系列顶点缓冲区
to an actual buffer, to an actual vertex buffer, or a series of vertex buffers
这取决于我们实际上如果组织这个
depending on how we actually organized this
因此, 为了代替我们每次在绘制之前都明确指定顶点布局
so, instead of us having to actually explicitly specify the vertex layout every time before we draw
好吧, 再说一次, 所以现在
well, again, so right now
显然, 我们没有绘制任何复杂的东西
obviously we're not drawing anything complex
所以对于那些刚刚接触OpenGL的人来说, 这可能有点困难
so it might be a little bit difficult for those of you who are new to OpenGL
为了真正理解我的意思
to actually get what I mean by this
但是我们现在绘制这个需要做的
but what we actually need to do currently to draw this
如果我有多个
if we had multiple
如果屏幕上有多个对象
if we had multiple objects in the screen
多个网格, 多个顶点缓冲区所有这些
multiple meshes, multiple vertex buffers all of that
就是我们基本上需要绑定顶点缓冲区
is we would basically have to bind our vertex buffer
绑定索引缓冲区, 然后绘制实际的对象
bind our index buffer, and then draw our actual object
但在我们绑定顶点缓冲区之后
but after we bind the vertex buffer
我们实际上也需要指定那个布局
we also need to actually specify that layout
因为如果我们以后
because if we later on
如果我们后面继续绑定另一个有不同的层的顶点缓冲区
if we later down the road bind another vertex buffer which has a different layer
那么我们必须有一种方式来表示那个, 好吧
then we have to actually have a way of saying that, well
这个缓冲区是用这个布局, 而另一个缓冲区是用其他布局的
this buffer has this layout, and this buffer has the other layout
它实际上并没有存储在缓冲区中
it's not actually stored in the buffer
你可能会认为, 因为我们实际上在代码中绑定了一个缓冲区
you might think that because we actually in our code we bind a buffer
然后我们实际上调用了这个vertexAttribPointer
and then we actually call this vertexAttribPointer
这个状态与实际缓冲区对象绑定并保存在一起
that this state is kind of tied to and saved with this actual buffer object
但事实并非如此, 这实际上是与顶点数组对象有技术联系的
but it's not, this is something that is actually technically tied to a vertex array object
因此, 我们每次都需要调用它
and thus we need to call it every time
事实上, 让我们看看我们的代码会是什么样子。
in fact, let's take a look at what our code would look like
如果我们真的绑定了每次渲染所需的所有内容
if we were actually kind of binding everything that we needed to render every time
因为现在, 我们所做的是
because right now, what we've done is
我们已经绑定了我们所拥有的所有类型的对象
we've bound all of the kind of objects that we have
因为我们每种只有一个
because we only have one of each
我们有一个着色器, 一个顶点缓冲区, 或者一个索引缓冲区
we have one shader, we have one vertex buffer, or one index buffer
以及所有这些
and all of that
如果我们真的有多个对象
if we actually would have multiple objects
我们每次都必须重新绑定当前绘制所需的所有东西
we would have to rebind everything we need for the current drawer every time
那么让我们来看看, 那会是什么样子
so let's take a look at what that will look like
我要做的是, 当我们把一切都设置好的时候
what I'm going to do is, when we actually set everything up
在这里, 我实际上要解绑一切
over here, I'm actually going to unbind everything
所以我要调用glBindBuffer
so I'm going to call glBindBuffer
事实上, 让我从这里复制所有代码
in fact, let me just copy everything from here
那么我们需要这个glBindBuffer
so we need bind buffer, we need binds
需要这个我们索引缓冲区或元素缓冲区的glBindBuffer
we need this bind buffer which is our index buffer or our element buffer
然后我们需要这个glUseProgram
and then we have this use program
好的, 所以我要做的就是基本上把所有这些都调用0, 对吧
okay, so what I'm going to do is basically called zero for all of these, right
所以glUseProgram(0)
so glUseProgram zero
和glBindBuffer(GL_ARRAY_BUFFER, 0)以及索引缓冲区
and bind buffer zero for array buffer and index buffer
所以我在这里做的是, 我基本上解绑了所有的东西
so what I've done here is, I've basically unbound everything
那么到了绘制的时候
so when it comes time to draw
我们需要做的是
what we need to do is
实际上绑定我们需要的所有东西, 让这个绘制元素工作
actually bind everything that we need, for this draw elements to work
这样我们才能正确地渲染所有东西
so that we render everything correctly
这将包括, 你知道, 设置, 我们可能需要的任何一种状态
and this will include, you know, setting up, any kind of state that we may need
在这个例子中是非常非常简单的
in this example is very very simple
所以我们真正需要做的就是绑定这些东西
so all we really need to do is just bind these things
好吧, 那么在我们绘制这个之前
right, so before we draw this
我将通过调用glUseProgram绑定这个着色器, 对吧
I'm going to bind this shader, right, by calling glUseProgram
然后一旦那个绑定好了, 我们可以设置统一变量
and then we can set the uniform once that's bound
然后我要绑定我的缓冲区, 就是个缓冲区
then I'm going to bind my buffer, which is going to be just buffer
然后我将绑定我的索引缓冲区, 我相信我们叫它ibo
and then I'm going to bind my index buffer which I believe we called ibo
好了, 很酷, 还有我真正需要做的, 这在这里可能并不明显
okay, cool, and what I actually need to do, which might not be apparent here
我还需要用到这个glVertexAttribPointer, 然后再次运行它
is I also need to get this glVertexAttribPointer, and run that again
现在, 如果最后是disableVertexAttribArray, 你可能会
now, you will probably, if you end up disableVertexAttribArray
你可能需要再做一次, 所以让我们复制一下这个
you probably have to do that again, so let's just copy this
就这整个代码块, 因为我们可能像那样需要它, 好了
and this whole block here, because we might need it like that, okay
所以这就是它最终的样子
so this is what it kind of ends up looking like
我们绑定着色器, 设置统一变量, 绑定顶点缓冲区
we bind our shader, we set up our uniforms, we bind our vertex buffer
我们设置顶点缓冲区的布局, 最后绑定索引缓冲区
we set up the layout of that vertex buffer, and then finally we bind our index buffer
然后我们调用glDrawElements, 让我们运行这段代码
and then we call glDrawElements, let's run this code
看看会发生什么
and see what happens
你可以看到, 我们得到了和以前一样的结果, 完美
you can see, we get the same result as before, perfect
所以这里有趣的是这两个
so the part that is interesting here is these two
我们是否每次都要这样做, 答案是肯定的
do we have to do these every time, and the answer is well yes
因为它们可能已经改变了, 如果我们用不同的布局绘制另一个对象
because they may have changed, if we draw another object with a different layout
所以顶点数组对象实际上就是包含这种状态的对象
so vertex array objects are actually what contained this state
因此, 如果我们正确地利用顶点数组对象
so if we utilize vertex array objects properly, and work to do
例如, 为几何体的每个部分创建不同的顶点数组对象
for example, make a different vertex array object for each piece of geometry
我们实际上在绘制的, 或者基本上在每个DrawCall指令发出时
that we actually draw or for each DrawCall basically
然后理论上我们只需要绑定顶点数组对象
then all we would need to do theoretically is just bind the vertex array object
就这样, 我们做完了
and that's it, we're done
因为顶点数组对象将包含顶点缓冲区之间的绑定
because a vertex array object will contain a binding between a vertex buffer or buffers
以及实际的顶点规范或顶点到布局
and that actual kind of vertex specification or that vertex to layout
所以换句话说
so in other words
vertexAttribPointer实际上会绑定一个实际的顶点缓冲区和数组缓冲区
so in other words, vertexAttribPointer actually will bind an actual vertex buffer and array buffer
所以一些东西绑定到这个GL_ARRAY_BUFFER插槽
so something bound to this GL_ARRAY_BUFFER slot
它会将其与具有该规范的实际层绑定
it will bind that with that actual layer with that specification
无论你是否有一个像我们这里一样的独立缓冲区, 这都是有效的
and that works whether or not you have a single buffer like we do here
或者如果你有多个缓冲区
or if you have multiple buffers
我们以后最终肯定也会讨论
and we'll definitely end up talking about
单缓冲区和多顶点缓冲区
kind of a single buffer and multiple vertex buffers in the future as well
因此, 我们绘制方式的改变从
and so the way that we draw things changes from being
绑定我们的着色器
bind our shader
绑定我们的顶点缓冲区, 设置顶点布局, 绑定我们的索引缓冲区
bind our vertex buffer, set up the vertex layout, bind our index buffer
然后实际发出那个DrawCall指令
and then actually issue that DrawCall
它从那个变成了, 绑定我们的着色器
it changes from that to just being bind our shader
因为很明显, 这是不变的
because obviously that stays the same
然后我们绑定顶点数组, 然后绑定索引缓冲区
then we bind our vertex array, and then we bind our index buffer
然后最终我们应该发出DrawCall指令
and then finally we should that DrawCall
所以基本上是绑定顶点缓冲区并设置其布局
so basically binding that vertex buffer and setting up its layout
只是变成了绑定顶点数组对象
just becomes binding that vertex array object
因为它包含了我们实际需要的所有状态
because that contains all the state that we actually need
我需要在这里提到的一件事是
one of the thing that I need to mention here is that
从技术上讲, 顶点数组对象是必需的
technically speaking vertex array objects are mandatory
它们现在正在被使用
and they are actually in use right now
这就是为什么我说即使我们没有创建它们
which is why I said that even without us creating them
这个状态仍由顶点数组对象保持
this state is still maintained by the vertex array object
这个东西就是OpenGL兼容性配置文件
the thing is the OpenGL compatibility profile
这就是我们在这里实际运行的
which is what we're actually running here
就像OpenGL基本上运行的一种模式
is like a mode for OpenGL basically running
默认情况下, 兼容性配置文件实际上为我们创建了一个顶点数组对象
the compatibility profile actually creates a vertex array object for us by default
并且那就是这个0的作用
and that's what zero is
然而, 核心配置文件没有
whereas the core profile does not
所以我们实际上需要自己显式地创建一个OpenGL顶点数组对象
so we actually need to explicitly create an OpenGL vertex array object by ourselves
绑定它, 确保一切正常
and bind it, and make sure that's all up and running
如果我们正在使用核心配置文件, 需要手动处理
manually if we're using the core profile
为了证明这一点, 我将要做
so to demonstrate this, what I'm going to do
我要点击f5, 我的绘制代码, 看看是否一切都正常运行
I'm just going to hit f5 draw my code just to see if everything's running correctly
你可以看到它是这样的
and you can see it is
我现在要做的就是
what I'm going to do now is
告诉GLFW我想创建一个上下文, 这个OpenGL上下文
actually tell GLFW that I want to create a context, this OpenGL context
实际上, 我想在这个上下文中用核心配置文件创建这个窗口
I actually want to create this window in this context with the core profile
我要做的是
and the way I'm going to do this is
基本上只需在这里粘贴这个代码
basically just by pasting this code here
所以我在这里做的是设置一个glfwWindowHint
so what I'm doing here is I'm setting a glfwWindowHint
这说明我希望我的主要版本是OpenGL 3
which says that I want my major version to be OpenGL three
次版本是3, 所以是OpenGL 3.3
minor version to be three, so it's OpenGL 3.3
然后这是这里的重要代码
and then this is the important code here
设置我的OpenGL配置是核心配置文件
I'm setting my OpenGL profile to be core
现在, 我已经有了兼容配置文件(COMPAT)
now currently I've got compatibility on
所以如果我实际上设置这个是兼容配置文件, 然后按f5
so if I actually just set this to combat profile, and hit f5
你会注意到的唯一变化是我们的OpenGL的实际版本
the only thing that you'll notice the changes is our actual version of OpenGL
而不是使用我们的驱动程序中提供的绝对最新版本
instead of using the absolute latest one that we have available in our drivers
它使用的是3.3, 这当然是我指定的
it's using 3.3, which of course is the one that I specified
你可以看到, 当然, 我的代码仍然可以完美地工作
and you can see that, of course, my code still works perfectly
但是, 如果我把它改成这样的核心配置文件, 并按f5
however, if I change this to be the core profile like this, and hit our f5
我们实际上会触发一个断言, 如你所见
we're actually going to trigger an assert as you can see
当我们尝试启用这个vertexAttribArray的时候
when we try and enable this vertexAttribArray
这是因为, 如果我们在这里进入OpenGL文档
and that is because, if we go over here into the OpenGL documentation here
这个关于顶点规范的hkronos站点实际上非常好
this hkronos site on vertex specification is actually really really good
你可以看到高亮的这行
and you can see the line of highlighted here
兼容OpenGL配置文件使VAO对象零成为默认对象
the compatibility OpenGL profile makes VAO object zero a default object
而核心配置不是, 它根本不是一个对象, 明白吗
whereas core does not, it's not an object at all, right
那就是这里实际发生的事情
that's what's actually happening here
正如你所看到的, 特别的是, 如果我们看一下这里的实际控制台
as you can see, specifically, if we look at our actual console here
我们看到了一个OpenGL错误码1282, 这是无效操作
we have an OpenGL error 1282, which is gl invalid operation
在enableVertexAttribArray这行代码中
on this line of code enableVertexAttribArray
让我们再次打开文档, 看看glEnableVertexAttribArray
so let's again, open the documentation, and look at glEnableVertexAttribArray
看看1282的真正含义
and see what 1282 actually means
你可以在这里看到, 这个导致无效操作的原因之一就是
and you can see over here, that one of the causes of this invalid operation
就是当没有绑定顶点数组对象的时候
is if no vertex array object is bound
这就是发生的事情, 我们没有绑定顶点数组对象
so that's what's happening, we don't have a vertex array object bound
因此, 我们无法指定顶点属性类型的规范或enableVertexAttribArray
therefore we cannot specify a vertex attribute kind of specification or enableVertexAttribArray
那么, 在核心配置文件中, 我们修复这个需要做的
so what we need to do now to fix this in the core profile
就是实际上创建那个VAO, 也就是顶点数组对象
is actually create that VAO, that vertex array object
那么让我们来实现那个吧, 它真的很简单
so let's do that, it's really easy to do this
我要做的就是在我们真正生成这个缓冲区并创建之前
all I'm going to do is before we actually generate this buffer and created
我将输入一个 unsigned int vao, 它将保存实际的顶点数组对象id
I'm going to type an unsigned int vao, which will hold that actual vertex array object id
然后是GLCall(glGenVertexArrays)
and then going to GLCall glGenVertexArrays
我将生成其中一个, 然后将那个id保存在vao变量中
I'm going to generate one of them, and then store that id in that vao variable
当然, 它和缓冲区是一样的, 除了生成顶点数组之外
so it's the same as with buffer as of course except we're generating vertex arrays
最后我要使用glBindVertexArray绑定它
and then finally I'm going to bind it and glBindVertexArray
这儿没有实际的目标
there's no actual target
所以我们只需要像这样指定要绑定的对象的id
so we just specify the id of what we want to bind like this
所以我没没有像GL_ARRAY_BUFFER这样的目标
so we don't have a target like GL_ARRAY_BUFFER or anything
它只是绑定顶点数组, 然后就用这个id
it's just bound vertex array, and then the id
而我仍然使用的核心配置文件
so I've still got the core profile on
这是之前用OpenGL错误断言的
which is what asserted before with an OpenGL error
现在让我们试着运行它, 看看会发生什么
let's try and run this now, and see what happens
你可以看到
and you can see
我没有得到任何错误, 我仍然得到相同的结果
I don't get any errors, and I still get the same result
好了, 这就是我们显式地创建一个vao
okay, so that is us explicitly creating a vao
这也是你使用VAO的具体方式
and that's specifically how you use VAO as well
我们只是生成一个顶点数组对象, 然后绑定它
we just generate one, we bind it
然后我们就可以实际绑定一个缓冲区, 并为它指定一个布局
and then we have the ability to actually bind a buffer, and specify a layout for it
现在, 真正有趣的是如果我们向下滚动到这儿
now, what's really interesting is that if we scroll down here
我们不再需要实际执行这个enableVertexAttribPointer代码, 明白吧
we no longer have to actually do this enableVertexAttribPointer code, okay
我们也不需要实际绑定缓冲区
and we also don't need to actually bind the buffer
让我们添加这个gl, 为了清除我们所有的gl状态
let's add to this gl, well, to us clearing all of our gl states
glBindVertexArray, 所以我们将绑定顶点数组为零
glBindVertexArray, so we'll be binding vertex array zero
只是为了让我们把一切都清理干净
just so we're clearing everything
然后在这里, 我要绑定顶点数组vao
and then over here, I'm just going to bind vertex array vao
那么你可以看到
so you can see that
我根本没有绑定顶点缓冲区
I'm not binding my vertex buffer at all
and then over here, I'm just going to bind vertex array vao
我根本没有绑定顶点缓冲区
I'm not binding my vertex buffer at all
当前绑定到GL_ARRAY_BUFFER插槽的缓冲区实际上是零, 对吧
and the currently bound buffer to GL_ARRAY_BUFFER is actually zero, right
我只绑定了我的顶点数组
I'm just binding my vertex array
然后绑定我的索引缓冲区, 就这样, 好吧
and just binding my index buffer, and that's it, okay
显然, 我也绑定了着色器
obviously I'm binding my shader as well
然后发出那个DrawCall指令, 让我们按f5, 看看这个
and then issuing that DrawCall. let's hit f5, check that out
我仍然可以正确地进行矩形渲染
I still get my rectangle rendering correctly
所以实际上发生的是
so what's actually happening
是将该顶点缓冲区链接到这个顶点数组对象的位置
is where linking that vertex buffer to this vertex array object
问题是, 到底是什么代码实现了那个
and the question is what code is actually doing that
这可能有点让人困惑
and it might be a little bit confusing
如果你不知道它的原理
if you don't know how it works
但当然, 我会告诉你它的原理
but of course, I'm going to tell you how it works
当我们绑定顶点数组和缓冲区的时候
when we bind a vertex array and we bind a buffer
实际上没有东西去链接这两个
nothing actually links the two
但当我们实际上指定这个vertexAttribPointer的时候
but when we actually specify this vertexAttribPointer
我们说的是这个顶点数组的索引为零的位置
we're saying index zero of this vertex array
将实际绑定到当前绑定的GL_ARRAY_BUFFER插槽, 明白吗
is going to actually be bound to the currently bound GL_ARRAY_BUFFER, okay
换句话说, 这就是
so this in other words
这是一行实际链接这个缓冲区的代码
it's a line of code that actually links this buffer
通过这个vao
with this vao
对吧, 如果然后我绑定一个不同的缓冲区
okay, if I was then to bind a different buffer
然后调用带有索引1的glVertexAttribPointer
and then call glVertexAttribPointer that with the index one
在启用, 当然使用这行代码
after enabling, of course using this line
然后我会说, 在这个数组缓冲区内
then I would actually be saying, that inside this array buffer
索引1实际上指向不同的顶点缓冲区
index one is actually pointing to a different vertex buffer
同样, 我们将来肯定会讨论多个顶点缓冲区
and again, we'll definitely talk about multiple vertex buffers in the future
以及在一个缓冲区中包含一切, 就在一个缓冲区中
as well as having one buffer with everything, in one buffer
因为那也是一种选择
because that's also an option
所以那就是它实际的原理
so that's how it actually works
因为我们实际上指定了这个vertexAttribPointer
and because we've actually specified this vertexAttribPointer
我们绑定了一个顶点, 也绑定了一个实际的缓冲区
and we have a vertex right bound, and we have an actual buffer bound
基本上就是把两个链接起来
the two are basically linked
这意味着我们要做的一切就是
which means that all we have to do
绑定我们的顶点数组和索引缓冲区
is just bind our vertex array and then index buffers
当然, 完全是另一回事
of course for a separate thing completely
这也是我们仍然需要绑定它的原因
which is why we still need to bind it
然后我们就是绘制元素了, 而你也可以看到
and then we can draw elements, so you can see
这段代码已经变得相当干净了
this code has become quite a bit cleaner
这就是我们要做的一切
and that's all we have to actually do
所以最大的问题是我该怎么做
so the big question is what do I do
我应该一直使用顶点数组对象吗
am I supposed to use vertex array objects like all the time
我可以根据顶点规范设置顶点缓冲区吗
do I can I just be setting a vertex buffer from a vertex specification
什么是最优的
what's optimal
比如我怎么做, 所有这些问题
like how do I do things, all these questions
当我们要绘制多个网格时会发生什么
what happens when we have multiple meshes that we want to draw
我知道很多事情都非常简单
I know that a lot of this is incredibly kind of simple
因为我们只绘制了一个对象
because we're just drawing one object
而这真的非常简单
and it happens to be really really simple
我将开始把所有这些代码抽象成类, 而一旦我那样做了
I am going to start abstracting all of this code out into classes, and as soon as I do that
我想在下一期真的要开始做那个了
I think I want to actually start doing that next episode
那个一做完
as soon as that's done
这对我们来说真的很容易做到
it's going to be really easy for us to
实际上, 创建一组不同的顶点缓冲区
actually create a bunch of different vertex buffers
用数据填充它们, 并在屏幕上绘制多个对象
fill them with data, and draw multiple objects on the screen
我们可能需要设置一些其他的东西, 比如数学等等
and we'll probably have to set up some other things like maths and all of that
为了做到那一点
to make that happen
但是这个想法就像什么样的, 如何处理
but the idea is what's the like what is the deal like
我应该使用多个顶点数组对象吗
should I be using multiple vertex array objects
我能不用它们吗
can I get away without using them
如何处理
what's the deal
现在, 我要告诉你的是
now, what I'm about to tell you is going to be
有点固执己见, 可能有点含糊不清
a little bit opinionated and probably a bit vague
但问题是没有更好的办法让我向你解释
but the thing is there's no better way for me to actually explain it to you
因为答案是视情况而定
because the answer is it depends
那么首先, 让我们来看看这里发生了什么。
so first of all, let's take a look at what's happening here
如果我们使用我当前使用的核心配置文件
if we use the core profile which I'm currently using
我们必须创建一个顶点数组对象
we have to create a vertex array object
如果我们只使用兼容性配置文件
if we just use the compatibility profile
这并不意味着没有顶点数组对象
it doesn't mean there are no vertex array objects
这只意味着我们有一个默认的
it just means that we have one default
我们有一个默认的顶点数组对象, 它被绑定并设置为供我们使用
we have a default one, that's bound and set up for us to use
如果使用的核心配置文件, 我们必须自己创造一个
if we're in core, we have to create one ourselves
现在, 技术上你可以做的是, 你可以创造一个
now, what you could do technically is you could just create one
像这里我们做的一样创建一个顶点数组对象
create one vertex array object like we did here
在你整个项目的过程中, 都把它放在一边
and just leave it bound for the duration of your entire program
因此, 始终有一个绑定的顶点数组对象
so you always have one vertex array object bound
然后你可以绑定一个顶点缓冲区并指定一个顶点布局
and then what you can do is bind a vertex buffer and specify a vertex layout
每次在绘制几何体之前
every time before you actually end up drawing your geometry
换句话说, 你在做和我们一样的事情
so in other words, you're kind of doing the same thing that we did
在我们介绍这个顶点数组对象之前
before we introduce this vertex array object
就好像我们在使用兼容性配置文件一样
so as if we were using that compatibility profile
那是一种选项
that is an option
那是你表示的一种方式
and that's kind of, that kind of a way for you to say
我完全忽略顶点数组对象
I'm ignoring vertex array objects entirely
我只是自己绑定了一种默认的
I'm just binding one kind of default one by myself
因为我需要这样做, 否则我的程序将无法运行
because I need to, otherwise my program won't run
否则我将无法渲染任何东西
otherwise I won't be able to render anything
因为OpenGL实际上在核心配置文件中规定了这一点
because OpenGL actually mandates that in the core profile
所以那是一种选项
so that is one option
通过绑定一个顶点数组对象, 可以忽略该顶点数组对象
you could just ignore vertex array objects by binding one
忘记它, 丢在一边
forgetting about it, leaving it bound
然后, 每次你实际上要绘制一些东西时
and then, every time you actually have to draw something
你已经绑定了一个顶点缓冲区
you spit you bind a vertex buffer
你绑定了一些东西到GL_ARRAY_BUFFER插槽中
you bind something into the GL_ARRAY_BUFFER slot
然后指定启用任何vertexAttribArray
then you specify that you enable any vertexAttribArray
你不得不指定那个vertexAttribPointer
you have to and specify that vertexAttribPointer stuff
这样你就可以映射你的布局了
so that you map your layout
然后绑定索引缓冲区, 然后渲染, 对吧
and then you bind your index buffer, and then you render, right
很明显, 在任何其他状态下都有一个着色器
and obviously you have a shader abound in any other state
你可能不得不设置一下, 对吧
that you might have to set up, right
你可以做那个
you could do that
那是一个选项, 那就是选项A
that's one option, that's option a
选项B是对于你创建的几何体的每一块
option b is for every piece of geometry that you create
基本上创建一个顶点数组对象
you basically create a vertex array object
然后指定那个规范一次
then you specify that specification once
那么你就可以启用你需要的任何vertexAttribArray了
so you enable any vertexAttribArray you need to
可以根据需要多次指定glVertexAttribPointer
you specify glVertexAttribPointer as many times as you need
把那些都设置好
to set all of that stuff up
然后, 在执行所有这些操作之前, 你将看到绑定顶点缓冲区
and then you'll see bind vertex buffers as well before you do all that
然后到了绘制的时候
and then when it comes time to draw
基本上只需绑定不同的顶点数组对象
you just bind a different vertex array object basically
每次在你绘制几何体之前
every time before you draw your geometry
然后将其绑定到索引缓冲区中
and then you bind it in an index buffer
然后你就可以调用glDrawElements
and then you call glDrawElements
或者你用的任何绘制函数, 好吧
or whatever draw function you're using, okay
所以你基本上可以在整个项目中有一个全局VAO
so you basically you either have one global VAO for the entire program
然后每次绑定不同的缓冲区和不同的顶点规范
and then you bind different buffers and different vertex specifications every time
或者你对每个几何体或唯一几何体或任何东西都有单独的VAO, 对吧
or you have a separate VAO for each piece of geometry or each unique piece of geometry or whatever, right
哪一个更好, 还是很难回答
which one's better, again, it's hard to answer
所以一个更好更容易回答的问题是
so a better an easier question to answer is
哪一个更优秀
which one is more optimal
我应该用哪一个, 哪一个更快
which one should I use which one is faster
只绑定缓冲区并在每次布局时指定该规范是否更快
is it faster to just bind a buffer and specify that specification every time that layout
或者每次绑定不同的VAO是否更快
or can I or is it faster to bind a different VAO every time
现在, 在过去, 有一个VAO的速度更快
now, in the past, it has been faster to actually just have one VAO
然后每次绑定一切
and then bind everything every time
我知道这是事实, NVIDIA实际上有一篇关于这方面的研究
I know that for a fact, and NVIDIA actually has a paper on that
描述中的某个链接
a link something in the description
我觉得是67页PPT之类的
it's like I think slide 67 or something of that
我这儿只是凭记忆说的
I'm really just talking from memory here
一个源引擎或着阀源引擎
of a source engine, valve source engine
他们实际上嫉妒的那种表现, 阻止了VAO的使用
kind of presentation where they actually envious physically, discouraged the use of VAO
然后说不要用它们
and said just don't use them
那是很久以前的事了
that was a while ago
我最近没有做过这方面的基准测试
I haven't done any recent benchmarks on this
所以我建议你使用VAO, 对吧
so what I would recommend for you to do is use the VAO, right
就使用它们, OpenGL建议你使用它们
just use them, OpenGL recommends that you use them
所以就使用VAO
so use them
现在只是因为规范建议你做一些事情
now just because of specification recommends that you do something
这并不意味着这是最好的选择, 对吧
does not mean that it is the best thing to do, okay
这是一个真实的世界
this is the real world
与理想情况下VAO的工作原理略有不同
things work a little bit differently than the ideal case where VAO just work
对吧, 它们很快
right, and they're faster
所以我建议你做的是, 如果你真的关心性能
so what I recommend you do is that, if you really really care about performance
你绝对需要从这一切中挤出最后一点性能
and you absolutely need to squeeze every last bit of performance out of all this
实际上你需要进行一些测试
you actually run some tests
所以在你的环境中, 在你的平台上, 在你的设备中
so in your environment, on your platform, on your device
不管你实际上在做什么
whatever it is that you're actually doing
在你的实际生产环境中进行尝试
try in your actual production environment
尝试实际使用一个全局VAO与对每个对象使用一个VAO
try to actually use one global VAO vs a VAO for each object
看看从中得到一些真实的数字
and see get some real numbers out of that
看看什么对你更好
and see what works better for you
因为这将是视情况而定的
because it is going to be circumstantial
这将是不同的
it is going to be different
取决于你的环境
depending on your environment
因此, 在你的环境中对那个配置文件进行基准测试
so benchmark that profile that in your environment
看看哪个选项更适合你
and see whatever option works better for you
然后选择对你更好的, 好吧
and then stick with the one that works better for you, okay
我真的很难回答这样的问题
it's really difficult for me to answer questions like this
因为它是视情况而定的, 对吧
because it depends, right
再说一次, 我最近没有做过这方面的基准测试
again, I haven't done any recent benchmarks on this
在过去, 我发现使用一个全局VAO更快
in the past, I have found using one global VAO to be faster
但那是多年前的事了
but that was years ago
所以我现在不能以现在的驱动谈论这个
so I cannot talk about this right now with current drivers
那么我以后能做的就是
so what am I doing the future is
实际上, 对这种引擎或我们现在拥有的任何东西进行基准测试
actually benchmark this this kind of engine or whatever that we have right now
这个小沙盒应用程序
this little sandbox application
这个还不够成熟
there's no way near mature enough
没有足够的东西让我去测试它
doesn't have enough stuff going on for me to actually test it
否则我可能会做一个小基准测试
otherwise I would probably throw a little benchmark
事实上是的, 如果你想让我做个基准测试, 请在下面留言
actually yeah drop a comment below, if you want me to benchmark this
我会看看我能做些什么
and I'll see what I can do
如果你自己进行压力测试, 对这个做基准测试, 做所有的事情
if you yourself run a stress test and benchmark this and do all that
你可以在下面的评论中留下你的结果
you can leave your results in the comments below
我很想看它们
I'd love to read them
但这个想法是, 这取决于你是否想使用VAO
but the idea is again, it kind of depends whether or not you want to use VAO
从现在起我将使用VAO
I will from now on be using VAO
只是因为我现在并不特别关心性能
just because I don't particularly care about performance right now
并且这也是OpenGL建议你实际执行的操作
and it is what OpenGL recommends that you actually do
不过, 一定要看看我在评论部分链接的那篇文章或演示文稿
however, do check out that paper or presentation or whatever that I linked in the comment section
在下面的说明框中
in the description box below
如果你对此感兴趣, 并确定在你的环境中为你的用例测试它
if you're interested in that and definitely test it in your environment for your use case
你知道, 在你的平台上, 在你的设备上, 不管什么，实际上你会看到
you know, on your platform on your device whatever to actually see
你得到了什么, 因为这才是真正重要的
what you get, because that's what actually matters
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 可以点击那个喜欢按钮
if you did, you can hit the like button
如果你想支持我在这个频道所做的一切
if you want to support everything that I do here on this channel
那就去patreon.com/theCherno
then head on over to patreon.com/theCherno
你将得到一些很酷的奖励
you'll get some cool rewards
比如更早得到视频
such as getting videos early
访问我在此频道制作的每个系列的所有源代码存储库
access to all the source repositories for every series that I make on this channel
包括我今天在这里写的所有代码
including all the code that I've written here today as well
它就像每一期之间的差异
it's like a diff between each episode
这样你就可以很容易地看到任何添加的内容, 以及所有这些
so that you can easily see whatever added, and all of that
还有一些很酷的奖励
there's some other pretty cool rewards
例如, 像所有合作伙伴一样, 就是patreon上面的赞助人
like for example all of the partners, which is the highest patreon tier
我们每个人来聚会, 比如一个月一次
all of us we hang-out, like once a month
就像一个小时的生活对话
and just have like an hour long conversation about life
关于编程, 关于开发等等
and about programming and about developing and all that
那真是一段美好的时光
that's a really great time
所以一定要看看那些奖励
so definitely check out those rewards there
你做的最大的事情显然是帮助我继续制作新视频
the biggest thing you're doing is obviously helping me to continue making new videos
这是比较酷的
which is pretty cool and
像往常一样, 向每个人大声说出
as always a huge shout out to everyone
就是支持我的那些人
who supports what I do
因为没有你的支持, 这是不可能的
because without you, not this would be possible
下次, 我想我们要么谈谈数学
next time, I think we're either going to talk about maths
要么可能会开始抽象所有这些代码
we're going to probably start extracting all this code out
让我知道你的想法
let me know what you want to think
让我知道你想看什么, 请在下面评论区留言
let me know what you want to see in the comment section below
我们会看到我们最终在做什么
and we'll see what we actually end up doing
我想提的一件事是
one thing I wanted to mention was
如果我们谈论数学, 我们将不得不使用数学库
if we talk about maths, we'll have to use a math library
以及可能谈论
as well as probably talk about
你知道投影矩阵是怎么工作的吗
you know how things like projection matrices work
还有一般的矩阵等等
and matrices in general and all that
这可能是一件很长的事情, 但这是我们必须做的事情
so that might be a long thing, but it is something we have to do
所以, 你唯一会做的, 我唯一能说的
so, the only thing you can, the only thing I can say
我可以说, 关于数学, 你必须学会热爱它
I can say, about maths is you gotta learn to love it
因为作为一个图形程序员
because as a graphics programmer
你要学很多数学
you're gonna be dealing with maths quite a lot
因为几乎所有的事情都是这样运行的
because that's how pretty much everything works
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
下次见, 拜
I will see you guys next time, goodbye